=== PAGE 1 ===
Received 18 April 2023, accepted 17 May 2023, date of publication 24 May 2023, date of current version 1 June 2023.
Digital Object Identifier 10.1 109/ACCESS.2023.3279819
Detection of Ransomware Attacks Using
Processor and Disk Usage Data
KUMAR THUMMAPUDI
 , PALDEN LAMA,
AND RAJENDRA V. BOPPANA
 , (Senior Member, IEEE)
Department of Computer Science, The University of Texas at San Antonio, San Antonio, TX 78249, USA
Corresponding author: Rajendra V. Boppana (rajendra.boppana@utsa.edu)
This research was partially supported by funding from the U.S. National Security Agency under Contracts H98230-21-1-0171 and
#FA8075-18-D-0008/FA807520F0060 (as a subcontract D9104-S4/SCI-10607 through the Georgia Tech Research Institute).
ABSTRACT Ransomware often evades antivirus tools, encrypts files, and renders the target computer and
its data unusable. The current approaches to detect such ransomware include monitoring processes, system
calls, and file activities on the target system and analyzing the data collected. Monitoring multiple processes
has a very high overhead; newer ransomware may interfere with the monitoring and corrupt the collected
data. This paper presents a robust and practical approach to detecting ransomware in execution on a virtual
machine (VM). We collect data for selected processor and disk I/O events for the entire VM from the host
machine and use a machine learning (ML) classifier to develop a detection model. This approach avoids
the overhead of continuously monitoring every process on the target machine and prevents the risk of data
contamination by ransomware. Furthermore, it is resilient to variations in user workloads. It provides fast
detection with a high probability for known (used for training the ML model) and unknown (not used for
training) ransomware. The random forest (RF) classifier performed the best of the seven ML classifiers
we tested. Over six different user loads and 22 ransomware, the RF model detected ransomware within
400 milliseconds with a 0.98 probability.
INDEX TERMS Deep learning, disk statistics, hardware performance counters, machine learning, ran-
somware, virtual machines.
I. INTRODUCTION
Ransomware is malware that encrypts files on a target com-
puter or locks the computer to render the target machine and
its data unusable. Cyber attackers use ransomware attacks
to extort victimsÆ money. Nation-state actors may use ran-
somware attacks to inflict harm on the critical infrastructure
of their adversaries. These attacks are often combined with
the exfiltration of victimsÆ data to compel the victim to pay a
ransom or sell the data on the dark web. In 2022 around 70%
of businesses were victimized by ransomware attacks [1].
Ransomware is expected to attack a business, consumer,
or device every 2 seconds by 2031, up from every 11 seconds
in 2021. The damage cost was $20 billion in 2021 and is likely
The associate editor coordinating the review of this manuscript and
approving it for publication was Vicente Alarcon-Aquino
 .to exceed $265 Billion By 2031 [2]. Several researchers have
recently investigated the detection of ransomware attacks.
Signature-based detection [3], [4] relies on the hash values
generated by antivirus software for known ransomware and
checks the target machine for files that match the hash values.
However, polymorphic and metamorphic versions of previ-
ously known ransomware can bypass such signature-based
detection [4], [5]. Therefore, behavioral or runtime detection
of ransomware in execution complements signature-based
detection methods. The behavioral analysis is a dynamic
analysis that looks into the virusÆs behaviorùthe sequence
of actions performed by the ransomware after it infects the
victim machine. While malware activities vary widely, ran-
somware must perform a specific sequence of activities to
encrypt as many data files as possible quickly. Some recent
ransomware such as LockBit2.0, Darkside, and BlackMatter
encrypt only parts (the first few bytes) of files to render
VOLUME 11, 2023This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 License.
For more information, see https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ 51395

=== PAGE 2 ===
K. Thummapudi et al.: Detection of Ransomware Attacks Using Processor and Disk Usage Data
more files unusable quickly [6]. Therefore, the requirement
of quickly encrypting user files is likely to differentiate ran-
somwareÆs runtime behavior from that of a benign applica-
tion. The premise is that a system under ransomware attack
must exhibit some form of immutable anomalous behavior.
For example, the ransomware must access files from the hard
disk and use the processor for data encryption resulting in
elevated activity; suitably trained machine-learning methods
may detect the elevated activity.
Runtime detection implemented on the target machine
requires continual monitoring of various processes or com-
ponents and subsystems, collecting data related to various
events, and analyzing the data for anomalous behavior [7],
[8]. Ransomware may try camouflaging its runtime behavior
by creating additional processes and activities. However, the
fact remains that a system under attack exhibits some form of
elevated activity, which is detectable with appropriate anal-
ysis. Runtime detection is resource-intensive and intrusive if
the monitoring is done on the target machine since the process
corresponding to ransomware may not be easy to identify, and
multiple processes must be monitored. Also, such monitoring
is prone to be disabled by the ransomware designed to shut
down active processes before encrypting files.
Hardware performance counters (HPCs) are special-
purpose registers that count processor and system events
per process or the entire system. The current processors
can count hundreds of processor and system events, such
as the number of instructions executed, cache misses, and
accesses to off-chip memory. The data collected using HPCs
are frequently used for performance analysis and tuning of
the system software. However, several recent research efforts
have investigated their use for malware detection [9], [10],
[11], [12], [13], [14]. Alam et al. [15] utilized HPC data
collected for each process running on the system. However,
monitoring many processes is impractical as it can cripple the
systemÆs performance. Pundir et al. [7] collected the data at
the machine level. However, their experiments are limited to
a single workload of a Windows virtual machine (VM), and a
change in the workload of a VM (varying the number of appli-
cations) may significantly impact the detection accuracy.
This paper investigates the fast detection of ransomware in
execution on a Windows 10 virtual machine (VM). We collect
both the HPC and disk I/O data at the host-machine level. The
target (VM) is ignorant of the monitoring and data collection;
also, there is little or no impact on its performance. We use
machine learning (ML)-based models to analyze the data and
detect ransomware in execution. Our method is particularly
suited for protecting users of VMs in a cloud environment.
The key contributions of this paper are as follows.
òWe present an approach to detect ransomware accurately
using HPC and disk I/O data observed from the host
machine. Our approach avoids the overhead of moni-
toring many processes on the target machine and pre-
vents data contamination by the ransomware designed
to thwart such monitoring activities.òWe evaluate the detection effectiveness under different
user workloads. To the best of our knowledge, we are the
first to analyze the impact of workload variation on the
runtime detection of active ransomware. Furthermore,
we demonstrate that machine learning (ML) and deep
learning (DL) based detection models improve detection
accuracy when trained with varying workloads.
òWe demonstrate that combining the HPC and disk I/O
data to build an ML-based detection model can improve
the detection accuracy compared to using a model based
on HPC or I/O data alone.
òOur ML models can detect ransomware within a few
hundred milliseconds of the start of ransomware exe-
cution with high probability, even with varying user
workloads.
òWe make the experimental datasets, codes, and scripts
used in this study freely available to all researchers
for further investigations and verification of our
results [16], [17], [18], [19], [20].
The rest of the paper is organized as follows: Section II
reviews the literature on runtime ransomware detection. Sec-
tion III describes the experimental setup and the tools used.
Section IV describes the ML models used. Section V presents
the results of the detection of ransomware activity. Section VI
concludes the paper.
II. BACKGROUND AND PRIOR WORK
This section focuses on the current work on HPC-based mal-
ware or ransomware detection mechanisms. We also briefly
discussed other detection techniques and their limitations.
We summarize the most relevant works, data collection
methodologies, ML classifiers, and performance analyses in
Table 1.
A. FILE AND I/O BASED MALWARE DETECTION
Many approaches have been proposed to detect crypto-
ransomware activity using file I/O operations [22], [23], [24],
[25], [26]. For example, Kharraz et al. [27], [28] presented
UNVEIL, a dynamic analysis system, to detect ransomware
activity by observing the filesystem I/O activity such as writ-
ing and delete of various benign and malicious applications.
Despite a high 0.96 TPR (true positive rate, also called recall)
with zero false positives, their experiments are designed
to identify ransomware samples that are not in execution.
Similarly, Continella et al. [29] proposed ShieldFS, an add-
on driver, to make Windows native filesystem immune to
ransomware attacks. They collect benign I/O access patterns
on real-world machines and malicious access patterns by
running ransomware in a controlled environment. A custom
ML classifier is trained on the filesystem activity of collected
samples and is leveraged at runtime to detect malicious activ-
ity. Likewise, Shukla et al. [30] tried to expose the gaps in
existing works and proposed a customized FileTracker which
learns new behavior while under attack by ransomware.
51396 VOLUME 11, 2023

=== PAGE 3 ===
K. Thummapudi et al.: Detection of Ransomware Attacks Using Processor and Disk Usage Data
TABLE 1. Comparison of the most relevant results on ransomware detection. Random Forest (RF), Decision Trees (DT), Gradient Boost (GB), eXtreme
Gradient Boost (XGB), Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM). Benignware (BW), Ransomware (RW).
On the other hand, Scaife et al. [31] used file type changes,
similarity measure, and Shannon entropy as primary indica-
tors and presented, Crypto-Drop, an early-warning detection
system. However, their model fails to differentiate between
benign and malicious encryption. Similarly, Mehnaz et al. [8]
introduced a hybrid ransomware detection mechanism,
RWGuard, that uses entropy for file change monitoring and
decoy techniques. Meanwhile, Sgandurra et al. [32] proposed
a framework called EldeRan to identify dynamic features
of ransomware using the ML classifierRegularized Logistic
Regression. EldeRan observes Windows API calls, Registry
Key operations, File I/O operations, and strings in binaries
as features. Similarly, Zavarsky et al. [33] demonstrated that
ransomware detection is possible on Windows and Android
devices by monitoring abnormal filesystem and registry activ-
ities.Most of the above detection mechanisms intercept filesys-
tem I/O requests that pass through the I/O scheduler, ana-
lyze various features like decoy file access, access patterns,
entropy, and file types, and suspend or kill the process based
on the engine/model decision. Such a detection mechanism
could lead to a single-point failure where the attacker can
manipulate the detection engine as it also resides inside
the same OS (operating system) under attack. Besides that,
an entropy-based identification may fail to identify the differ-
ence between benign and malicious encryption. Furthermore,
an entropy-based identification could lead to false alarms
due to high entropy resulting from a benign activity such as
file compression [34]. Similarly, Genc et al. [35] explored the
limitations of existing decoy-based ransomware mitigation
strategies by implementing a proof-of-concept anti-decoy
ransomware and showed that it could bypass an existing
VOLUME 11, 2023 51397

=== PAGE 4 ===
K. Thummapudi et al.: Detection of Ransomware Attacks Using Processor and Disk Usage Data
decoy-based technique. They also proposed possible solu-
tions to mitigate anti-decoy ransomware.
B. OTHER MALWARE DETECTION
Besides filesystem-based detection, a few works explored the
possibility of identifying ransomware based on its short-lived
activities [36], [37], [38], [39]. Ahmadian et al. [40] proposed
an approach called Connection-Monitor & Connection-
Breaker which observes DNS requests assuming that
most ransomware Command & Control center domains
are generated by Domain Generation Algorithms (DGAs).
Kolodenker et al. [41] proposed a prototype called PayBreak
which holds the symmetric keys as escrow to thwart unau-
thorized encryption. The prototype relies on the insight that
attackers heavily rely on Crypto-API provided by the OS
under attack. Recent ransomware developers include a copy
of the crypto-library in their code to bypass this protection
technique. Kiraz et al. [42], on the other hand, proposed an
approach called ExpMonitor which builds on the concept
that most crypto-ransomware use public-key cryptographic
algorithms which involve large integer arithmetic.
C. HPC-BASED MALWARE DETECTION
Zhou et al. [13] studied the usability of HPCs for malware
detection. They conducted an extensive study of 2000 pro-
grams, including malware and benignware applications.
They argued that there is no causation between low-level
microarchitectural events and high-level software behavior.
Das et al. [11] extensively studied the state-of-the-art work
on using HPCs for security. They proved the high fidelity of
HPCs at the process level and how ransomware can manipu-
late them.
On the contrary, Malone et al. [34] generated signatures
of benign applications using the HPC data. They claimed
that HPC data could be used to identify the deviations
in the behavior of a program from its normal behav-
ior. Demme et al. [9] investigated the feasibility of malware
detection using HPCs and ML classifiers. The authors claim
that their models identify the malware with an accuracy of
about 0.90. Their study was conducted on Android, ARM,
and Intel Linux platforms, while most ransomware specif-
ically targets Windows OS [43]. Similarly, Tang et al. [10]
proposed unsupervised anomaly-based malware detection
using HPCs. They used the ML classifiers to train on the
expected behavior of Windows programs, and any deviation
from it is considered malicious. The work is focused on
malware other than ransomware. Kadiyala et al. [12] pro-
posed an HPC-based fine-grained malware detection through
a three-step process of extracting HPCs of the system calls,
dimensionality reduction, and feeding the components to an
ML classifier. Aurangzeb et al. [14] tried to identify the dif-
ference between ransomware and non-ransomware malware
using HPCs data and ML classifiers such as RF, decision trees
(DT), gradient boost (GBoost), and extreme gradient boost
(XGBoost).Alam et al. [15] used HPCs to detect ransomware activity
and proposed a framework called RATAFIA with the help
of a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) based autoencoder
and Fast Fourier Transformation. The perf tool [44] was
used to collect HPC events data such as branches, branch-
misses, cache-misses, and cache-references. They used a
window-based technique to compare the behavioral patterns
of ransomware and normal systems. While this work is con-
ducted in a sandbox environment, their framework is for Unix
operating systems. Pundir et al. [7] proposed a quicker detec-
tion technique, RanStop. They used the likwid tool [45] to
capture HPC event data at an interval of 100 Ás for 20 times-
tamps. They analyzed 80 crypto-ransomware using Recursive
Neural Networks (RNNs), LSTM, and Global Average Pool-
ing (GAP) for noise reduction. The authors claim to detect
ransomware activity in less than 2 ms with an accuracy of
0.97. However, the experiments are conducted on a VM with
no user activity. Therefore, any change in the user activity
would affect the results. The other possible limitation of
the technique is the duration of the data collection, 2 ms.
Most recent ransomware acts stealthy and may not exhibit
malicious behavior in such a short period.
III. EXPERIMENTAL SETUP
This section describes the experimental setup, the applica-
tions and ransomware used, and the data collection process.
A. TESTBED AND DATA COLLECTION
We used a bare-metal instance with dual Intel(R) Xeon(R)
Gold 6240R CPUs (central processing units) at 2.40GHz
clock rate on the Chameleon cloud [46], with Ubuntu
20.04.3 LTS as the host operating system (OS). We set up
a Windows 10 VM on top of a Kernel-based Virtual Machine
(KVM) hypervisor. The VM is the target of ransomware
attacks. We consider the Windows 10 OS for the target owing
to its popularity with ransomware developers. Eight virtual
CPUs (vCPUs) out of the available ninety-six are pinned to
the VM to ensure consistent allocation of resources to the
VM.
To capture the variations in HPC and I/O data due to vary-
ing user activities, we configure the target VM with different
user workloads ranging from an idle machine to a heavily
loaded machine running tens of user applications. The three
primary workloads are (1) Base-Load (BL.0): no user activ-
ities, only the default Windows system activities; (2) CPU-
intensive Load (CL.0): about 10 Windows applications, such
as MS Office applications, document reader, image viewer,
movie player, browser windows loaded with Alexa top-10
websites [47], running on top of the base load; (3) Network-
intensive Load (NL.0): more than 30 Windows applications
installed from Ninite [48], such as OneDrive, GoogleDrive,
and Microsoft Teams. Three additional secondary workload
variants (CL.1, CL.2, and NL.1) are generated by varying
the number of applications specified in one of the primary
workload variants. We created six different snapshots of the
VM, each with a specific level of user workload. The user
51398 VOLUME 11, 2023

=== PAGE 5 ===
K. Thummapudi et al.: Detection of Ransomware Attacks Using Processor and Disk Usage Data
workloads can have a significant impact on the data collected
(Section IV-A) and on the detection accuracy (Section V-D).
From the host machine, We collect HPC values for pro-
cessor, memory, and system events of the process that cor-
responds to the VM using the perf tool [44] and disk I/O
stats of the virtual disk allocated to the VM using the virsh
tool [49] with the domblkstats option. Sampling the events
at the host level ensures that ransomware running on the
VM cannot directly interfere with the data collection process.
Since we collect HPC and disk I/O data at the host machine
level and treat the guest OS as a black box, the choice of the
OS used for the guest machine will not significantly impact
the experimental setup or the data collection methodology.
We collected over 100 ransomware samples downloaded
from Virusshare [50]. We selected twenty-two ransomware
samples that encrypted one or more files on the infected
machine within the first 60 seconds of their execution. Table 2
gives the selected ransomware with their hashes and family
names. For easier reference, we indicate the ransomware by
the four-character strings at the start of their filenames.
Our selection includes ransomware samples that are active
and able to encrypt. Some ransomware samples in our list
start encrypting/modifying files immediately. The other ran-
somware samples stay quiet or scope the system and become
active only towards the end of the 1-minute period we used
for experiments. Figure 1shows the percentage of files each
ransomware encrypted. Out of the 22 ransomware samples,
12 encrypted at least 50% of some 9,500 user files within
the first minute, six encrypted 10-40% of the files, while the
remaining four encrypted less than 5% of the files. Therefore,
our selection included a wide range of ransomware encryp-
tion behavior.
We also selected three benign applicationsû7zip, aesCrypt,
and sDelete, which use operations such as compressing data,
encrypting data, and deleting files likely to be used by ran-
somware and exhibit ransomware-like behavior. We selected
these three benign applications to help the detection models
differentiate malicious and benign activities that are similar
more accurately. Our default benign case is with VM running
none of the benign or ransomware codes; we call it a dryRun.
Therefore, we ran 26 applications (22 ransomware and four
benign cases) on each of the six snapshots.
Each run starts with a clean copy of one of the six snapshots
and the execution of a benign or ransomware application.
The benign applications are pre-installed on the snapshot and
are initiated to perform a task that lasts at least 60 seconds.
Ransomware applications are copied to the VM before their
execution. Once a benign application or ransomware starts,
we collect, on the host machine, the HPC and I/O data of
the process that corresponds to the VM for approximately
60 seconds. Figure 2depicts the workflow for data collection.
The sampling interval determines the detection speed. So a
short sampling interval is desired, provided the data can be
collected without loss or errors. The perftool allows sam-
pling intervals as short as 1 ms. We tried multiple sampling
intervals, including 1 ms, 5 ms, 10 ms, and 100 ms for HPCevents. The 5 ms interval provided a tradeoff between latency
and consistency of data collection. For the disk I/O stats,
the minimum sampling interval feasible with domblkstats is
20 ms; the data collected was consistent at this interval. So we
used that as the sampling interval for disk I/O data collection.
Therefore, in all our experiments, the HPC events are sampled
in 5 ms intervals for a total of 12,000 times using the perf
tool, and the disk I/O events are sampled in 20 ms intervals
for a total of 3000 times using virsh domblkstats. A data trace
consists of the HPC and disk I/O samples collected for an
application run.
B. FEATURE SELECTION
A data instance is the primary data unit used for training or
testing. An HPC data instance consists of forty consecutive
HPC samples, and an I/O data instance ten consecutive disk
I/O samples. Each trace has 300 nonoverlapping HPC and
I/O data instances. We tried various HPC instance sizes with
the number of samples per instance in the range [10, 1000].
We determined that 200 ms instances with 40 samples provide
a good tradeoff between ransomware detection accuracy and
latency. Since HPC data provided better prediction results
than disk I/O data, we also used 200 ms for disk instances.
For the LSTM classifier, we used the raw HPC and I/O data
contributing to each instance as inputs to the models. For all
other classifiers, we computed statistics from the raw data for
each instance and used them as inputs to the models. We com-
puted four statistical featuresûthe mean, median, standard
deviation, and inter-quartile range (IQR) for each instance.
The mean and standard deviation are likely sufficient; how-
ever, we included the median and IQR to handle any pos-
sible skewed data distributions resulting from ransomware
selectively active for very short durations. (We tested various
combinations of statistical features to train and test the HPC
model. The model trained using the four statistical features
of 5 HPC events outperformed the model trained with other
combinations of events. The same is the case with the Disk-
I/O model as well.)
The current Intel processors have three fixed counters
that count instructions executed, reference cycles, and clock
cycles and four programmable counters, which can be con-
figured to count hundreds of processor events [51]. However,
attempting to count more than four events at a time using
the programmable counters leads to time-multiplexing of the
events, which seems to result in inconsistent readings. There-
fore, our experiments limited the number of events counted
using the programmable counters to four. We used the fol-
lowing feature selection process to determine the specific
four HPC events to count using the programmable counters.
We started with a list of 40 HPC events that we identified
as the most likely events impacted by ransomware activity.
Table 3lists these events. We ran each application ten times
to collect the data for these 40 HPC events with four pro-
grammable events specified per run. To capture the varia-
tions in experimental conditions and ransomware behavior,
VOLUME 11, 2023 51399

